<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<sessions>
    <entry>
        <entryId>0</entryId>
        <sessionId>0</sessionId>
        <chair>Marina Martinic Kavur</chair>
        <sessionName>Molecular Toolbox</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Jan Ellenberg</presenterName>
        <department>Cell Biology &amp; Biophysics Unit</department>
        <affiliation>EMBL, Heidelberg</affiliation>
        <imageId>ellenberg</imageId>
        <title>Systems biology of cell division using light microscopy</title>
        <date>November 3rd</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>9:45 - 10:45</time>
        <keyNote>1</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>Cell division is fundamental to all life. In somatic cells it drives the continuous renewal of tissues, in the embryo the rapid proliferation of totipotent cells. We have developed advanced light microscopy tools to study both in a systematic and quantitative manner. Using systematic gene silencing by RNAi and subsequent phenotyping by high-throughput microscopy we have defined ~600 genes that are required for a human cell to divide faithfully during somatic mitosis. To understand the resulting dynamic protein networks and their orchestration in space and time, we have established an integrated systems biology workflow. After homozygous genome editing to tag all endogenous copies of a given mitotic protein fluorescently, we image its absolute abundance and subcellular distribution by calibrated 4D imaging relative to spatio-temporal landmarks. Computational image analysis and modeling allows us to align cell morphology in space and time to obtain a standard mitotic cell into which we can integrate all protein data. Using image parameterization and machine learning, we measure the dynamic subcellular localization as well as fluxes between subcellular compartments and structures, which enables predictions of protein clusters, the chronological order of their formation and disassembly, and the abundance of their subunits. Our integrated computational and experimental method is generic and makes many dynamic cellular processes amenable to dynamic protein network analysis. Light-sheet imaging has revolutionized our understanding of cell division during embryonic development in many biological model systems. Early mammalian development, however, remained inaccessible due to high light sensitivity and demanding culture requirements. A newly developed inverted high-throughput capable light-sheet microscope enabled the first in toto imaging of preimplantation mouse development from zygote to blastocyst. Using computational cell tracking, lineage tree reconstruction, and fate assignment, we revealed when fate determination happens and that chromosome segregation problems and aneuploidy is relatively common in mouse embryos.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>1</entryId>
        <sessionId>0</sessionId>
        <chair>Marina Martinic Kavur</chair>
        <sessionName>Molecular Toolbox</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Steve Lever</presenterName>
        <department>Defence Science and Technology Laboratory (DSTL)</department>
        <affiliation>Salisbury, UK</affiliation>
        <imageId>lever</imageId>
        <title>Use of spider webs to determine the survival rate of filoviruses contained within aerosols</title>
        <date>November 3rd</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>10:45 - 11:20</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>The recent Ebola virus epidemic in West Africa has confirmed previous knowledge that filoviruses (Ebola virus and the closely related Marburg virus) are associated with high morbidity and mortality rates in humans. In addition, they are capable of human-to-human transmission, via infected material such as blood and other body fluids, and are believed to have low infectious doses for humans. Although Ebola virus is not naturally transmitted by the aerosol route, droplet spread may occur during an outbreak. In experimental model systems, filoviruses are able to infect via the respiratory route and are lethal at very low doses, but there is minimal information on how well filoviruses are able to survive within aerosol particles. There is also little known about how well filoviruses survive in liquids or on solid surfaces, which is important in the management of patients or samples that have been exposed to filoviruses. Understanding the ability to survive in an aerosol leads to better understanding of the hazard posed by pathogenic organisms and can inform decisions related to the control and management of disease outbreaks. DSTL have developed a method where aerosol droplets containing filoviruses can be captured using microthreads, in the form of spiders' webs, and the decay rates of different species of Ebolavirus and Marburgvirus were determined under different environmental conditions. In this presentation, data will be presented to show how the application of this technique has enabled the relative survival rate of filoviruses in aerosols and the potential infectivity of filoviruses to be determined.</abstract>
    </entry>


    <entry>
        <entryId>2</entryId>
        <sessionId>0</sessionId>
        <chair>Marina Martinic Kavur</chair>
        <sessionName>Molecular Toolbox</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Luke Alphey</presenterName>
        <department>The Pirbright Institute</department>
        <affiliation>Woking, UK</affiliation>
        <imageId>alphey</imageId>
        <title>Genetic control of mosquitoes</title>
        <date>November 3rd</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>11:20 – 11:55</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>The rise in dengue over the past 50 years, together with recent outbreaks of chikungunya and Zika, has highlighted the lack of sustainable and efficient control of its primary vector Aedes aegypti. The development of genetic control has enabled the creation of possible alternative tools to traditional methods against mosquitoes either through population replacement or population suppression. We have developed synthetic genetic circuits to produce "genetically sterile" males of the target pest species. These sterile male mosquitoes (male mosquitoes do not bite or transmit disease) are released continually over a wide area to mate with the target pest population; death of progeny due to inheritance of the transgene leads to decline of the target population. A key feature is that the method is 'self-limiting'; making it controllable, reliable and reversible, in contrast to methods where the genetic change needs to persist in the wild population. Genetic control strains based on this principle have now been developed for at least eight major insect pest species. Field trials for the lead Aedes aegypti strain, OX513A, have been successfully conducted in the Cayman Islands, Malaysia, Brazil and Panama. Target populations of this mosquito species were suppressed by over 90% relative to control populations, despite ongoing immigration from adjacent areas and differences in ecological and social settings. Public acceptance of the technology at the field sites has been good. Applications in agriculture and in conservation biology are also being actively considered.</abstract>
    </entry>



    <entry>
        <entryId>3</entryId>
        <sessionId>1</sessionId>
        <chair>Triin Laos</chair>
        <sessionName>Manipulating the Code</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Robert Grass</presenterName>
        <department>Department of Chemistry and Applied Biosciences</department>
        <affiliation>ETH Zürich, Switzerland</affiliation>
        <imageId>grass</imageId>
        <title>Replacing T-Rex for data: Using fossilized DNA for the long-term storage of information</title>
        <date>November 3rd</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>13:15 – 13:50</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>Some of the oldest information our society has access to is the genetic information of ancient species discovered in the DNA of fossil bone (up to 700'000 years old). However, DNA in solution or in our living bodies is a relatively vulnerable molecule, sensitive to light, radicals and even air (humidity). Inspired by the ancient samples we developed a chemical synthesis method for the fabrication of "Synthetic Fossils". This is a glass-like material, in which DNA is encapsulated, and in which DNA is as well protected as in the prehistoric specimens. Driven by the current developments in medical diagnostics, the cost of DNA synthesis (=writing) and sequencing (=reading) are rapidly decreasing, allowing us to envision DNA as a high-density medium for long-term information storage. Implementing a small prototype (ca. 100 kB of digital information) with error correction capabilities and simulation of long-term storage by accelerated aging, we were able to display the longevity of the data stored up to at least 1000 years. The discussion will also include the use of encapsulated DNA as tracers and as distributed sensors.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>4</entryId>
        <sessionId>1</sessionId>
        <chair>Triin Laos</chair>
        <sessionName>Manipulating the Code</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Jonathan Gootenberg</presenterName>
        <department>Department of Systems Biology</department>
        <affiliation>MIT, Cambridge, USA</affiliation>
        <imageId>gootenberg</imageId>
        <title>Beyond Cas9: Discovering single effector CRISPR tools</title>
        <date>November 3rd</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>13:50 – 14:25</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>CRISPR-based molecular tools such as Cas9 have been quickly adopted into basic biology due to their re-programmability and ease of use. By expanding the CRISPR toolset to other effector proteins, we can discover new qualities such as novel PAM sequences, increased specificity, and RNA targeting. I will discuss methods for discovering and characterizing new CRISPR effectors, such as Cpf1 and the RNA-targeting effector C2c2.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>5</entryId>
        <sessionId>1</sessionId>
        <chair>Triin Laos</chair>
        <sessionName>Manipulating the Code</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Jason Chin</presenterName>
        <department>Laboratory of Molecular Biology</department>
        <affiliation>Centre for Chemical &amp; Synthetic Biology, Cambridge, UK</affiliation>
        <imageId>chin</imageId>
        <title>Reprogramming the genetic code</title>
        <date>November 3rd</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>14:55 – 15:55</time>
        <keyNote>1</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>The information for synthesizing the molecules that allow organisms to survive and replicate is encoded in genomic DNA. In the cell, DNA is copied to messenger RNA, and triplet codons (64) in the messenger RNA are decoded - in the process of translation - to synthesize polymers of the natural 20 amino acids. This process (DNA RNA protein) describes the central dogma of molecular biology and is conserved in terrestrial life. We are interested in re-writing the central dogma to create organisms that synthesize proteins containing unnatural amino acids and polymers composed of monomer building blocks beyond the 20 natural amino acids. I will discuss our invention and synthetic evolution of new "orthogonal" translational components (including ribosomes and aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases) to address the major challenges in re-writing the central dogma of biology. I will discuss the application of the approaches we have developed for incorporating unnatural amino acids into proteins and investigating and synthetically controlling diverse biological processes, with a particular emphasis on understanding the role of post-translational modifications.</abstract>
    </entry>



    <entry>
        <entryId>6</entryId>
        <sessionId>2</sessionId>
        <chair>Madalena Pinto</chair>
        <sessionName>Bioengineering Medicine</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Eric Vivier</presenterName>
        <department>Centre d'Immunologie de Marseille-Luminy (CIML)</department>
        <affiliation>Faculty of Science Aix-Marseille University, France</affiliation>
        <imageId>vivier</imageId>
        <title>Innate Lymphoid Cells: From discovery to clinical manipulations</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>09:00 – 10:00</time>
        <keyNote>1</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>Innate Lymphoid Cells represent an emerging population of lymphocytes. ILCs include Natural Killer (NK) cells and three main subsets, ILC1, ILC2 and ILC3. In contrast to T and B cells, ILCs do not express antigen-specific receptors derived from gene rearrangements. Besides this major difference in their recognition repertoire, ILC and T cell subsets share striking similarities as ILC1, ILC2 and ILC3 are driven by T-bet, GATA-3 and RORg t transcription factors, and produce IFN-g, IL-5/IL-13 and IL-17/IL-22 respectively. In addition, NK cells are driven by Eomes and T-bet, can be cytolytic and produce IFN-g, inasmuch as CD8+ T cells. These common features led to suggest that ILCs might correspond to innate counterparts of T cells. Over the course of evolution, two highly parallel systems have thus emerged in which ILCs mimic the effector profile of T cell subsets. However, it is still unclear how the innate and adaptive immune systems integrate these two arms. We will review the emerging set of data showing that ILCs and T cells can exert redundant functions in natura in humans and in models of experimental disease in mice, and discuss how the overlapping functions of ILCs and T cells contribute to the robustness of immunity and hence to the fitness of the hosts.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>7</entryId>
        <sessionId>2</sessionId>
        <chair>Madalena Pinto</chair>
        <sessionName>Bioengineering Medicine</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Jean-Philippe Saint-Pierre</presenterName>
        <department>Faculty of Engineering, Department of Materials</department>
        <affiliation>Imperial College London, UK</affiliation>
        <imageId>pierre</imageId>
        <title>Designing bio-inspired materials for regenerative medicine</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Thursday</day>
        <time>10:00 - 10:35</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>The overarching goal of regenerative medicine is to restore tissue functions. In this talk, I will describe some of the recent advances made in The Stevens Group towards the development of novel biomaterials to achieve this goal. I will first discuss an array of projects aimed at improve osteochondral tissue regeneration with bio-inspired scaffold structures and functionalization innovations. Our work to induce cells to deposit collagen in a depth-dependent manner and to induce improved chondrogenesis via peptide-polymer conjugates, as well as hydrogels will be highlighted. In a second time, I will describe a first foray in the development of materials to mitigate tissue fibrosis. I will elaborate on our approach to identify extracellular matrix cues that are presented in response to protease released during inflammation and act as feedback loops to halt its deleterious effects and I will demonstrate how these specific biological cues can be used towards preventing tissue fibrosis. Finally, the ability to control topography and chemistry at the nanoscale offers exciting possibilities for stimulating growth of new tissue. Recent developments in this context will be discussed, with a focus on the development of nanoneedles that can be interfaced with tissues to modulate cellular responses towards in vivo tissue regeneration of large volumes of highly vascularized and hierarchically organized tissue.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>8</entryId>
        <sessionId>2</sessionId>
        <chair>Madalena Pinto</chair>
        <sessionName>Bioengineering Medicine</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Simon Ausländer</presenterName>
        <department>Department of Biosystems Science and Engineering</department>
        <affiliation>ETH Zürich, Switzerland</affiliation>
        <imageId>auslaender</imageId>
        <title>Engineering of gene circuits for mammalian cell-based applications</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>10:35 – 11:10</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>Synthetic gene switches provide mammalian cells the ability to fine-tune protein expression levels in an input-output relationship. Especially the design of gene switches responding to disease-related input molecules in the physiological concentration range offers great opportunities for cell-based biomedical applications. Customized mammalian cell lines engineered with such gene switches enables the detection of physiological amounts of immune cell-derived trigger molecules in human blood. Moreover, microencapsulated and implanted designer cells can also be used in cell therapy in order to autonomously detect disease states and produce a therapeutic response. The next generation of engineered mammalian cells advances from one-input to multi-input gene circuits that transform cells into sophisticated decision-making systems capable of performing complex information-processing tasks. Therefore, the components of multiple gene switches are connected to each other to build networks that follow input-programmable logic for advanced control of living cells. Post-transcriptional RNA controllers contribute to the design of large gene circuits by adding a new regulation layer and linking different transcriptional switches. In future, cells engineered with large gene circuits may logically respond to various disease-relevant input molecules at the same time thereby increasing the diagnostic precision as well as therapeutic intervention portfolio.</abstract>
    </entry>




    <entry>
        <entryId>9</entryId>
        <sessionId>3</sessionId>
        <chair>Jillian Augustine</chair>
        <sessionName>Shaping Ecosystems</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Hervé Vanderschuren</presenterName>
        <department>Department of Biology, Institute of Agricultural Sciences</department>
        <affiliation>ETH Zürich / University of Liège, Switzerland / Belgium</affiliation>
        <imageId>vanderschuren</imageId>
        <title>Stories from the lab, stories from the field: Advancing crop biotechnology</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>13:40 – 14:40</time>
        <keyNote>1</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>The use of crop biotechnology is steadily increasing in the agrosystems of industrialized countries. Recent advances in genome editing are anticipated to further accentuate this trend. Given its potential for low input agriculture, there is a need to bring the benefits of crop biotechnology to developing and emerging countries. The challenge goes beyond the mere generation of transgenic crops because development and deployment of genetically engineered crops require local capacities and support from the authorities. In the recent years, we have used biotechnological approaches to improve cassava, the most important root crop in the tropics. Cassava production and processing suffer from several constraints, including viral diseases, drought and post-harvest deterioration. A better understanding of crop responses to biotic and abiotic stresses combined with genetic engineering approaches can be particularly instrumental to generate plants with improved traits. We have used Omics approaches to characterize cassava response to stresses and to subsequently implement biotechnological approaches for trait improvement. Smallholders and industries in cassava growing regions need traits such as resistance against cassava mosaic and brown streak diseases, prolonged shelf-life, drought tolerance, modified starch and improved nutritional content. Importantly those technologies should be implemented in local germplasm to secure impact for the local value chains. We actively collaborate with local institutions for technology transfer and assessment of cassava technologies in the field.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>10</entryId>
        <sessionId>3</sessionId>
        <chair>Jillian Augustine</chair>
        <sessionName>Shaping Ecosystems</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Howard Griffiths</presenterName>
        <department>Department of Plant Sciences</department>
        <affiliation>University of Cambridge, UK</affiliation>
        <imageId>griffiths</imageId>
        <title>Can we, and should we, turbocharge photosynthesis to increase crop productivity?</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>15:00 – 15:35</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>A second green revolution is required for the sustainable production of foodstocks for a growing, increasingly urbanised population, at a time when farmers and food producers are faced with stagnating crop yields and an increasingly uncertain climatic conditions for crop growth. The world population also faces a crisis in terms of food consumption and health: in the developed world, 30% of food is wasted, whilst non-communicable diseases such as diabetes and coronary conditions are endemic; in the developing world, post-production food losses during storage, climatic instability and competition for potable water are already leading to local and national ethnic conflicts, disease and starvation. Whilst food redistribution could threaten economic stability, each kilo of cash crops could represent the export of around 250- 2500 kg (0.25 - 2.5 tonne) of scarce water resources from developing countries. Against these dilemmas, several approaches have been suggested to enhance the efficiency of harvesting sunlight by crop plants, including the introduction of the C4 pathway into crops such rice, or explorations to transfer some form of an algal or cyanobacterial carbon concentrating mechanism into higher plants. The talk will present some of the fundamental insights recently into these processes, with a focus on the operation algal Chlamydomonas CCM, and progress made in expressing some of these associated components in a higher plant platform. We will also explore the tremendous advances in fundamental understanding associated with the research, the technical challenges and threats that could limit the applicability, in the context of global food security.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>11</entryId>
        <sessionId>3</sessionId>
        <chair>Jillian Augustine</chair>
        <sessionName>Shaping Ecosystems</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Louise Horsfall</presenterName>
        <department>Biotechnology</department>
        <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, Scotland</affiliation>
        <imageId>horsfall</imageId>
        <title>Microbes and metal nanoparticles</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>15:35 – 16:10</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>0</addedDim>
        <abstract>Microorganisms have the potential to manufacture metallic nanoparticles, irrespective of the source of metal cations, and provide us with new particles with novel functions. To exploit this we are identifying and optimising genetic elements with an aim to increase nanoparticle production and control nanoparticle size and homogeneity; in effect standardising nanoparticle samples by using biology. Whilst developing this process we are exploring its application in the treatment of contaminated waste, water and land. For the former application we are working to remove copper from whisky distillery byproducts and for the latter application we are part of a larger collaboration aiming to financially incentivise land decontamination. After using phytoremediation to hyperaccumulate metal contaminants from the soil, plants are harvested, processed and used as a source of metals for bacterial nanoparticle synthesis. Both applications illustrate how synthetic biology might contribute to moving us towards a more circular economy.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>13</entryId>
        <sessionId>4</sessionId>
        <chair>Tiffany Su &amp; Jasmin Taubenschmid</chair>
        <sessionName>Bioengineering Medicine</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Serafeim Perdikis</presenterName>
        <department>Defitech Foundation Chair in Brain-Machine Interface (CNBI)</department>
        <affiliation>École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Switzerland</affiliation>
        <imageId>perdikis</imageId>
        <title>Brain-Computer Interaction: Principles and clinical applications</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>11:30 – 12:30</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>1</addedDim>
        <abstract>Brain-Computer Interface (BCI) technology has been established as the solution towards direct mind control by human individuals. Clinical BCI applications are the spearhead of the field and motor-disabled end-users have been shown to benefit from a variety of BCI prototypes for communication, assistive mobility, motor substitution and restoration, environmental control and, more recently, neurorehabilitation. Pre-clinical and real-world validation of current BCI prototypes are essential for identifying these principles that can alleviate the shortcomings in the state-of-the-art and maximize the added value of BCI applications. In this talk, I will provide an overview of such principles successfully applied by the CNBI laboratory of EPFL, as well as exemplary applications where those have been evaluated. Our laboratory develops non-invasive BCI systems based on electroencephalographic (EEG) signals and, thus, devoid of medical hazards, real-time, portable, relatively low-cost and minimally obtrusive. Our research is pushing forward asynchronous paradigms offering spontaneous, ecological interaction. Furthermore, we stand on the machine-learning way to BCI with emphasis on personalization and adaptability, coupled with mutual learning protocols, so that elaborate signal processing and pattern recognition methods are optimally combined with the user's learnable modulation of brain signals towards robustness and usability. Additionally, cognitive mental state monitoring is employed to shape or refine the interaction. Shared-control approaches allow smart, context-aware robotics to complement the BCI channel for fine-grained control and reduction of the user's mental workload. Last but not least, hybrid BCI designs exploit additional physiological signals to augment the BCI modality and enrich the control paradigm. The applicability and effectiveness of the aforementioned principles has been demonstrated in several exemplary applications evaluated with both able-bodied and motor-disabled end-users.</abstract>
    </entry>

    <entry>
        <entryId>14</entryId>
        <sessionId>4</sessionId>
        <chair>Jasmin Taubenschmid</chair>
        <sessionName>Shaping Ecosystems</sessionName>
        <presenterName>Filippa Lentzos</presenterName>
        <department>Department of Social Science, Health and Medicine</department>
        <affiliation>King's College London, UK</affiliation>
        <imageId>lentzos</imageId>
        <title>The misuse of biology: Are you on your guard?</title>
        <date>November 4th</date>
        <day>Friday</day>
        <time>16:30 – 17:30</time>
        <keyNote>0</keyNote>
        <addedDim>1</addedDim>
        <abstract>Trust in biologists is in a precarious position. Secrecy, safety breaches and controversial experiments are risking the reputation of biomedical science. At the same time, advances in biology and biomedicine are significantly eroding technological barriers to biological weapons.This lecture considers life scientists' essential part in strengthening the red line against the inadvertent and deliberate misuse of biology. It considers past biological warfare programmes to weaponize disease, the multilateral disarmament response to them, and the possibility of biological weapons use today.</abstract>
    </entry>

</sessions>

